Finding Aid for Virginia P. Moore Collection MS.3821
University of Tennessee Libraries, Special Collections
Virginia P. Moore Collection
1880-1940
MS.3821
University of Tennessee Libraries, Special Collections
2.5 Linear feet (5 boxes)
This collection contains letters, photographs, articles, notes, and other material documenting the work of Virginia P. Moore, an early home demonstration agent in Tennessee.
Moore, Virginia P., (Virginia Pearl)
Scope and Contents Note
This collection contains letters, photographs, articles, notes, and other material documenting the work of Virginia P. Moore, an early home demonstration agent in Tennessee, and later in Florida, during the first half of the 20th century. The collection is arranged into seven series - Series I, Personal Material, includes items of Moore's documenting her personal life such as a diary, calendars, event programs, and travel mementos. Series II, Correspondence, includes letters and postcards written to and from Moore. Notable correspondence includes a few letters to and from Tennessee politician Cordell Hull and his wife, Rose. Series III, Writings by Moore, is comprised of unpublished and published notes and articles by Moore. Most relate to her work in home demonstration or to the history of the field. Series IV, Writings by Others, includes newspaper and magazine articles written about Moore as well as material related to home demonstration work. Series V, Home Demonstration Work Material, includes documents related to Moore's work in Tennessee and Florida. Items include examples of club students' work, recipes, pamphlets, event programs, and reports. Series VI, Photographs, includes photographs and negatives of Moore and her work with home demonstration clubs, agents, fairs, and with rural school improvement efforts. Series VII, Oversize, includes all oversize material such as a photograph album documenting Moore's work in Tennessee from 1911-1912 along with large photographs and a few certificates.
Conditions Governing Access
Colletions are stored offsite, and a minimum of 24 hours is needed to retrieve these items for use. Researchers interested in consulting any of the collections are advised to contact Special Collections at special@utk.edu.
Previous Citation
Material in this collection was previously cited as part of MS.1546, MS.2201, and MS.2376.
Biographical/Historical Note
Virginia Pearl Moore was one of the first five home demonstration agents in the U. S. She served in this field of work in Tennessee and Florida from 1909-1946. Moore was born on July 7, 1880 to Armstead (1814-1884) and Louisa Virginia Crenshaw Moore (1844-1921) in Gallatin, Tennessee. After studying at Peabody Normal College in Nashville, Moore was named Tennessee's state organizer of School Improvement Work. In this capacity, she organized gardening and canning clubs in several Tennessee counties. In 1911, Moore was named the State Collaborator for Tennessee where she served until coming to the University of Tennessee as an Assistant Director and State Home Demonstration Agent in 1914. She resigned her post in 1919 to return to Gallatin to take care of her mother; after her mother's death in 1921, Moore accepted a position as Assistant Home Demonstrator Agent at Florida State College for Women at Tallahassee where she remained until retiring to Maple Valley, Tennessee in 1946. In June 1937, she was one of only two women invited to speak at the International Housing Congress in Paris, France. Virginia Moore died on May 31, 1950 and is buried in Mt. Olivet Cemetery in Nashville, Tennessee.
Subjects
Gardening; Home demonstration work -- United States -- History.; Home economics extension workers -- United States.; Women -- Tennessee -- History.
Container List
- Personal Material, 1927-1945, undated; I
  - Personal Diary and Calendars, 1927-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal and Biographical Information, 1928-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Event Programs, 1917 April 6-1945 October 20, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mementos from European Travel, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1908-1950, undated; II
  - Correspondence, 1908 June 22-1929 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1930 February 20-1939 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1943 May 8-1950 June 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Blank Postcards, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Writings by Moore, circa 1920-1940, undated; III
  - Various Writings by Moore, circa 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Moore's Notes and Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Moore's Writings on Home Demonstration Work in Florida, 1929-1938, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Recollections on Early Home Demonstration in Florida, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Questions on Home Sanitation to Make You Think," Home Improvement Series, 1931 August (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "A Review of a Few Steps in Home Demonstration Work, 1908-1938,", circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Tennessee's Early Tomato Club and Home Demonstration Work, From 1911-1919,", undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Moore's Research and Writings on Alvin C. York, 1919-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Recollection on Meeting Cordell Hull, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Moore's Writings on Dr. Seaman A. Knapp, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Writings by Others, 1918-1970, undated; IV
  - Articles about Moore, 1946, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Articles by Others, 1918 October 3-1919 February 10, 1937 January 21-1946 March, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1928 February 13-1943 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clippings from Extension Service Review, 1937 May-1942 September (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "A Brief Study of the History of Sumner County,", circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Home Demonstration Work Material, 1909-1946, undated; V
  - Pamphlets, 1909-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Work of Club Students, 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Recipes and Instructions, circa 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Travel Documents and Expenses, 1918 April-1920 November (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Cooperative Demonstration Work Meeting, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Silver Anniversary of Cooperative Demonstration Work, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Silver Jubilee Program at Florida State College for Women, 1930 June 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Housing and Town Planning Congress, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Home Demonstration Reports, 1911, 1930-1946, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Canning and Tomato Club Work in Tennessee, 1913-1919, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reports on Demonstration Work in Florida, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Canning Club Work in Tennessee,", 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Four-Year Program of Work for Members of Girls' Home Demonstration Clubs in Tennessee,", 1925 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Home Demonstration Work under the Smith-Lever Act, 1919-1924,", 1929 June (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 4-H Publications, 1929-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Extension Service Review, 1937 May (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Recollections of Extension History" by J. A. Evans, 1938 August (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "A History of Extension Work in Tennessee: Twenty-Five Years of Service to Rural Life, 1914-1939,", 1939 May (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Extension Work in Virginia: A Brief History, 1907-1940,", circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Epsilon Sigma Phi, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photographs, circa 1880-1940; VI
  - Canning, Field Work, Crops, circa 1910-1920 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Early Work in Tennessee, circa 1910-1920 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Schools (Maury High School, Oakland School), circa 1910-1920 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Short Courses, Picnics, Exhibits, circa 1910-1920 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Corn and Tomato Clubs, circa 1910-1920 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Portraits, circa 1880-1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Susie V. Powell Photographs and History, circa 1910-1926 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1910-1920 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Loose Scrapbook Photographs, circa 1912-1914 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Oversize, circa 1910-1920; VII
  - Scrapbook, circa 1912-1914 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, circa 1910-1920 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 4)